<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-babel-price-propagation-00"
ipr="trust200902">
<front>
<title>Pay per forward extension for Babel</title>
<author fullname="Justin Kilpatrick" initials="J." surname="Kilpatrick">
<organization>Althea Mesh</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Raleigh</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
</postal>
<email>justin@altheamesh.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day="01" month="October" year="2017"/>

<abstract>
<t>This document proposes an extension to the <xref target="BABEL"/>
routing protocol to propagate prices and other billing information
for the use of an external payment program.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="TODOs">
<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Pay per forward update TLV type: TBD</t>
  <t>Currency sub-TLV type: TBD</t>
</list></t>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>Pay per forward is a payment strategy in which prices are advertised as
monotonically increasing values much like the Babel metric. Each node adds some
arbitrary price that it will charge to route packets along a particular route.</t>

<t>When traffic is sent along that route payment follows with it. In the diagram
below B and C and advertising prices of 5 and 2 respectively for forwarding 
traffic to D. To send traffic to D, A would transfer 7 units of whatever
currency is specified in the advertisements to B along with the traffic. B
would then repeat this process with C, keeping all but 2 units of the original
price for itself. D then receives the traffic.</t>

<figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[
          5      2
   A ---- B ---- C ---- D
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>By adopting this specification routers essentially run two parallel Babel
networks, one set for free routes and advertisements and another for paid
routes and advertisements. These two sets of routes can be completely
different, have an overlap, or see free routes transformed into paid and vice
versa by routers attempting to make money or subsidize specific connections.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Operation">

<t>Routers advertise a new TLV price-propagation-update in addition to the
existing Babel update TLV. The price-propagation-update TLV must contain at least
one currency sub-TLV.</t>

</section>

<section title="Currency agreement">

<t>For each configured currency the router maintains a hop price that it wishes to
charge. When a price-propagation-update TLV is received each currency sub-TLV is
compared against the list of configured currencies for that router.</t>

<t>For each currency sub-TLV that matches a configured currency the hop price is
added to the currency sub-TLV advertisement price and the total value is stored
in the routing table for later advertisement.</t>

<t>Received currency sub-TLVs that are not in the routers supported currency list
MUST be discarded silently.</t>

<t>If there are no supported currency sub-TLVs in a pay-per-foward update TLV the
update itself must be discarded.</t>

</section>

<section title="Route transformation">

<t>Routers using this extension will continue to support normal Babel routes
and are free to transform free routes into paid route advertisements and vice
versa.</t>

</section>

<section title="Packet format">

<t>This extension defines the price-propagation-update TLV, whose
Type field has value [undecided]. The for the price-propagation
update TLV is otherwise identical to the existing update TLV. 
It is mandatory that a price-propagation TLV must contain at least 
one currency sub-TLV of the following format.</t>
</section>

<section title="Pay per forward currency sub-TLV">
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = TBD |    Length     |          Currency code          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Price per byte                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Fields:
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
<t hangText="Type">Set to TBD to indicate a Full path round trip time sub-TLV.</t>
<t hangText="Length">The length of the body, exclusive of the Type and Length fields.
                     A constant value of 6 bytes</t>
<t hangText="Currency code">A code defined by a standardized billing protocol representing 
                            both a currency and the unit denominated by the price per byte 
                            field. The currency code may also specify details around how 
                            payments must be delivered or handled.</t>
<t hangText="Price per byte">An unsigned integer denoting a quantity of currency 
                             defined by the currency code</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Security considerations">

<t>There are no serious security concerns arising for Babel itself as a result
of this extension. The payment implementation may be impacted by Babel.
Problems of that nature may result in updates to this document. </t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="BABEL"><front>
<title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date month="May" year="2017"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet Draft" value="draft-ietf-babel-rfc6126bis-02"/>
</reference>
</references>
</back>

</rfc>

