<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-babel-full-path-rtt-00"
ipr="trust200902">
<front>
<title>Full path round trip time extension for Babel</title>
<author fullname="Justin Kilpatrick" initials="J." surname="Kilpatrick">
<organization>Althea Mesh</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Raleigh</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
</postal>
<email>justin@altheamesh.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day="01" month="October" year="2017"/>

<abstract>

<t>This document proposes a <xref target="BABEL"/> extension that sums round
trip time  estimation provided by the existing experimental Babel per
neighbor <xref target="RTT"/> extension. To advertise the complete
round trip time along a path. The total path round trip time metric can then be directly
tested, validated, and used for routing decisions not subject to arbitrary
metric variation or route poisoning attacks.</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="TODOs">
<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Full path round trip time sub-TLV type: TBD</t>
  <t>Compatible security methods list</t>
</list></t>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>The existing Babel metric field is elegant in that it takes into account many
potential sources of willingness and route quality. While this is useful and
compact in a network of trusted routers operated by close communities, the
loose rules around metric computation for Babel make it impossible to
objectively compare routes.</t>

<t>The goal of this extension is to provide enough information to reduce or
eliminate the effectiveness of routing table poisoning attacks by verifying
objective information about the quality of the route using secured traffic
between the route originator and the destination.</t> 

<t>This document does not specify how this verification is to be carried out, the
main concern is with propagating the information required.</t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol operation">

<t>In the experimental Babel per neighbor <xref target="RTT"/> extension timestamps
are attached as sub-TLV's to hello and IHU TLV's. A similar set of timestamps can
be communicated over an entire route.</t>

<t>The sum of the round trip time estimations per neighbor and the whole path
round trip time should be the same. In reality there will always be some random
variation. For stable and performant routes variation should average out over time</t>

</section>

<section title="Boostrapping">

<t>For full path round trip time to be successfully and accurately computed the
entire path from the originator of the route must be running both experimental extensions</t>

<t>A router MAY at the time of creating an update TLV for a local route chose to
attach a full path round trip time sub-TLV. For the first hop the value is initialized
to zero.</t>

</section>

<section title="Updating the round trip time">

<t>Since updates may be sent to a broadcast address it is the receiver of the
update that computes the new round trip time sum to act on and store for later
propagation. This is done by storing the round trip time per neighbor as specified
in the  <xref target="RTT"/> extension and then adding the appropriate per neighbor
value to the timedelta recived in the full path round trip time sub-TLV.</t>

</section>

<section title="Retraction">

<t>If a update is to be sent out and a timestamp hello sub-TLV was not contained
in the last successful hello/IHU cycle a full path round trip time sub-TLV must not be
included in the update.</t>

<t>If an update is received for a route that does not include the an updated
path round trip time value the previously existing estimation MUST be removed 
from the routing table and no longer advertised. This protects against
stale values when the chain of round trip time estimation is somehow broken.</t>

</section>

<section title="Packet Format">

<t>This extension defines a Full path round trip time sub-TLV that is
contained within a update sub-TLV.</t>
</section>

<section title="Full path round trip time sub-TLV">
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Type = TBD |    Length     |        Transmit timedelta       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|             ...             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Fields:
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
<t hangText="Type">Set to [undecided] to indicate a full path round trip time sub-TLV</t>
<t hangText="Length">The length of the body, exclusive of the Type and length fields. In this case a constant 4 bytes</t>
<t hangText="Transmit timedelta">The total estimated microsectons required to send a packet along this route, stored as a 32 bit unsigned integer</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Security considerations">

<t>This extension imposes no significant security concerns for Babel.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="BABEL"><front>
<title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date month="May" year="2017"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet Draft" value="draft-ietf-babel-rfc6126bis-02"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RTT"><front>
<title>Delay-based Metric Extension for the Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Baptiste Jonglez" initials="B." surname="Jonglez"/>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date month="March" year="2004"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="84"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3704"/>
</reference>

</references>


</back>

</rfc>

